<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: swift | Doing things the hard way...]]></title>
  <link href="http://blog.diogot.com/blog/categories/swift/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://blog.diogot.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-09-30T21:45:33-03:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.diogot.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Diogo Tridapalli]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swift embedded runtime library increases app size]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.diogot.com/blog/2014/09/29/swift-embedded-runtime-library-increases-app-size/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-29T23:44:55-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.diogot.com/blog/2014/09/29/swift-embedded-runtime-library-increases-app-size</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Since beginning Swift attracted a lot of attention, one of many questions was: How Apple will guarantee backwards compatibility in future Swift releases?</p>

<p>The response is cited a few times at Swift Blog, like the <a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/blog/?id=14">post of 1.0 release</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Because your apps today embed a version of the Swift GM runtime, they will continue to run well into the future.</p></blockquote>

<p>But one thing, so far, I don&rsquo;t see people talking about is how this embedded library affect the size of an app?</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>The easiest way to discover is to create an empty project and compare the size.
I created two <em>Single View Application</em> projects using on Xcode 6.0.1. On the first image is the bundle directory of Objective-C app and on the second the Swift one.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/swift-lib-overhead.jpg" width="518" height="338" title="&lsquo;App bundle files and sizes&rsquo;" ></p>

<p>The Objective-C only app bundle takes only 192 KB and the Swift app bundle 8.6 MB. The Swift binary is smaller but the runtime frameworks can be a huge overhead for many apps!</p>

<p>On the second post of Swift Blog talk about <a href="https://developer.apple.com/swift/blog/?id=2">Compatibility</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>As Swift changes, those frameworks will be incompatible with the rest of your app. When the binary interface stabilizes in a year or two, the Swift runtime will become part of the host OS and this limitation will no longer exist.</p></blockquote>

<p>So for at least one year if you want to use Swift in your apps, you will have to accept this <em>little</em> overhead.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Update 2014/09/30</em>: Worth to mention that the runtime libraries are embedded on every app that supports Swift, no matter the minimum deployment target.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Swift, access control and testing]]></title>
    <link href="http://blog.diogot.com/blog/2014/08/23/swift_access_control_and_testing/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-23T22:04:31-03:00</updated>
    <id>http://blog.diogot.com/blog/2014/08/23/swift_access_control_and_testing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Access control in Swift looks nice, but can give some trouble to find out how to make tests work smoothly. (The code in this post works with Xcode 6 beta 6.)</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>There are three <a href="https://developer.apple.com/library/prerelease/ios/documentation/Swift/Conceptual/Swift_Programming_Language/Inheritance.html#//apple_ref/doc/uid/TP40014097-CH17-XID_251">Access Control</a> levels:</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Public access</em> enables entities to be used within any source file from their defining module, and also in a source file from another module that imports the defining module. You typically use public access when specifying the public interface to a framework.</li>
<li><em>Internal access</em> enables entities to be used within any source file from their defining module, but not in any source file outside of that module. You typically use internal access when defining an app’s or a framework’s internal structure.</li>
<li><em>Private access</em> restricts the use of an entity to its own defining source file. Use private access to hide the implementation details of a specific piece of functionality.”</li>
</ul>


<p>The default level is <em>Internal access</em>, this is fine, all your classes are visible only to your module, no imports, no external access. Although soon on later you will test your code, right?</p>

<p>First of all, XCTestCase are bundled on a different target and you don&rsquo;t include your classes to the test bundle, right? That&rsquo;s easy, just import the target that contains your class, if your target is called <code>MyProject</code> your test class will be like this:</p>

<pre><code>import UIKit
import XCText
import MyProject

class MyProjectTests: XCTestCase {
    func testMyProject() {
        XCTAssert(true, "Pass")
    }
}
</code></pre>

<p>But this is not enough, do you remember that the default access level is <code>Inernal</code>? If you don&rsquo;t change it in the class that will be tested the compiler will say something like: <code>Use of unresolved identifier 'MyClass'</code>. To void this just set your class and all the methods and properties that will be tested to <code>public</code>:</p>

<pre><code>public class MyClass: NSObject {
    public var prop: String
    public init() {}
}
</code></pre>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
